This video was recorded during a discussion between director Kihachi Okamoto and director Hideaki Anno for Animage magazine in 1996.
Thanks to the cooperation of Kihachi Productions, director Anno, and others involved, we are able to broadcast this video.
The video itself was not recorded for broadcast. We apologize in advance for the quality of the picture and sound, which may be difficult to catch.
Throughout this interview, we hope you can feel the joy and passion of making films.
The director known as the "Artisan of Entertainment", Kihachi Okamoto
Evangelion series director, Hideaki Anno
A rare video interview between the two is now available.
Kihachi Okamoto and Hideaki Anno at the former Okamoto residence in Ikuta, 1996.
The Screen
"Battle of Okinawa" is the movie I've seen the most times in my life. I've seen it over 100 times.
Why did you like it so much?
I think it's a physiological thing.
When I went to shoot "Battle of Okinawa," the area south of Mabuni
was still scattered with human bones.
There were monuments for the loyal souls of each prefecture
being built as if in competition with each other.
I thought it would be better to spend money
on collecting the bones and mourning than to build such things.
So I didn't like the southern part of that place itself because I had the feeling
that there would be dead bodies buried there, even where I was walking.
I'm jealous of Anno's work, because in anime you can put as many people as you want in a shot.
If it's a live action, every time you add an actor, it costs more money.
These days extras cost 6,800 yen per a day.
But back then it was paid in US dollars.
We didn't have enough money, so 19 members of us went to Okinawa to film.
But then 20-odd press people showed up there.
I was really pissed off. "Why are there more reporters than us?"
We couldn't afford enough actors, so I ended up in the film too. I played the role of the marine saying "I can't see the sea".
So you are in the film?
Yeah, because there weren't enough actors.
No wonder you said that you were jealous of anime filmmaking.
But of course I'm sure there must be tough things as well.
Yes there are. I'm in turn jealous of live-action filmmaking.
If I worked in animation, I would be jealous of live-action, and perhaps likewise vice versa.
So we both want what the other has.
You can't move the camera in animation.
Recently, we started using CGI and it helps making animation much easier.
But even so, some cuts just stink of CGI.
I can tell you're working pretty hard on it.
You make it look like people are moving by showing their shadows without moving the camera.
By shadows?
-Yeah.
In case of animation, I mainly use a fixed camera.
Or I can use a panning camera, too.
The tempo is good, too.
The tempo is directly influenced by Okamoto-san.
Thank you.
No one is doing it, but I believe that tempo is what's best for anime.
The charm of when you cut.
Not so much the content of the cut
I'm talking about the moment the shot changes. The satisfaction there.
I feel there's a lot of that in your films.
And it's exactly that which is best for anime.
Again, the amount of information given by a fixed camera,
and the moment the shot changes.
The change in silhouette when a character immediately switches
from the right side of the frame to the left via the cut.
Especially with the dull standard aspect ratio,
I think that's about the only thing you can do.
It's also great the way you use over-the-shoulder shot.
Especially with Cinescope, it's great to be able to do that, isn't it? It's a shame we don't have Cinescope now.
Even with the Vista, I feel the frame is just halfway there, and it's not good enough.
I hate standard aspect. But I don't like Vista either because it's not good enough.
Film by Cinescope is the best after all.
With CinemaScope, it's interesting how to fill in the empty spaces.
What do you mean by that?
For example, up to VistaVision size, both full shots and cowboy shots look good,
But when it comes to the CinemaScope size, whether you take a full shot or a cowboy shot,
you need to add something on both sides to make the shot look good.
But that makes it more interesting.
Also, with CinemaScope, the audience moves their heads
from right to left in the theater.
I don't think you can do that with TV.
That's why I think there's just no point if it's not CinemaScope.
The Long Shot
I was an assistant director for a good 15 years.
Generally, if directors don't have the obligation to teach the juniors, they also don't have the right to.
You gradually learn from small talks,
when you were having a chat, or in a taxi on the way to work.
I learned that when you take a zooming picture, the lens should zoom in as close as possible.
And then when you take a long shot, the camera should be pulled away from the subject as far as possible.
It's better to have some kind of trigger for the next cut to get a rhythm.
Even just tapping the ash off your cigarette, you can shoot it as a long shot.
I heard that's better than just going to the next cut.
In fact, it's all about how far the camera angle can be pulled away from the subject.
Right.
But that was pretty pulled back. For us, we'd call that a long shot.
It's an extreme long shot, isn't it?
So the difference between the movie theater,
video specialty, and TV specialty is the long shot.
For example, when you want to show emotions with a long shot instead of a close-up shot, the camera angle should be pulled pretty far away from the subject.
I think it's a matter of how far the camera can go away from the subject. It's easy to do in anime because you can express it with drawings.
But in that case, you can't make any mistakes with the drawing. If you're not a good enough illustrator, it's out of the question.
It depends on the painter, just as a good play depends on the actor.
It's the same in that respect.
Editing
Is the tempo of that editing a physiological thing?
Do you cut by intuition, or have you already decided where to cut by the time you shoot?
Well, it's already been decided before shooting.
The minimum is 2 frames, but at least I need 8 frames for a single blink of an actor.
So I feel 8 frames is important.
I've heard that it's 8 or 7 frames. And that to leave something in the viewers' minds without letting them confirm anything, it'd be 6 frames.
And that to make sure the viewers understand something, you need at least 9 frames.
I like using a multiple of 4. Like 8.
So if someone with slightly big eyes looks at it without blinking, I need 12 frames.
I like using 4 and 7. Even 2 frames are enough to leave an impression if it's a drawing.
Right, 2 frames has a subliminal effect?
That's a myth though, I think.
In the case of animation, the amount of information is limited because it's a drawing.
Therefore if the drawing is familiar to the viewer, even 2 frames are enough to leave an impression.
7 frames would be more than enough. If it's a moving image, 7 frames.
If it's a still image though, even 2 or 3 frames can be too much.
Of course, 1 frame is not enough to understand.
but 2 frames are definitely enough.
That's why I need 8 frames in a cut someone is running, 8 steps.
For walking, I feel 4 steps is enough.
So if I decide the number of steps is 4, changing the count to an odd number gives the impression that the character is in a bit of a hurry.
When it comes to battle scenes, I use 7 frames.
Right, I think it's better to use odd numbers in that situation.
I use 7 frames with the insert.
I actually shoot around 12 frames, and then in the cutting drop 3 frames or so. Maybe 6 or 5.
In the case of animation, I decide where to cut at the drawing stage.
except for AC (action cuts).
Also it depends on the tempo or the rhythm of the line.
It takes me about 12 hours to cut 20 minutes.
The longest one was 24 hours; over two days.
In my case, I usually have only 4 days to edit.
I did the editing of "EAST MEETS WEST" last year, and I had the same four days.
It really wasn't my tempo overall.
I found out afterward that I had a brain infarct.
So I had been acting a bit strange since last February.
If I had known I was sick, I would have spent another day or two editing and going through a lot of polishing.
If I could have done that once or twice.
I think the film would have had the tempo it has now.
But I was really bothered about it, so this spring I re-edited the film.
I didn't get my own tempo, so it bothered me so much.
I have a bit of a short temper.
For example, when I shoot a long scene, say 3-4 minutes, I might cut the opening and closing parts depending on if I'm annoyed.
I always cut off the last part of the cut, too.
It feels great when the scene changes right when the line ends.
Okamoto's films taught me that.
My films are just imitations,
so I can't help but feel embarrassed when you watch them.
No, I think you're right.
It takes so long to get there by yourself.
Reaction Shots
Fundamentally, the audience won't enjoy it if you don't enjoy it yourself.
Absolutely.
So you have to do what makes you feel good.
When you need a reaction shot, you show the side the viewers want to see.
If a character is attacking another in one cut,
the viewers want to see what kind of reaction the character on the defense has.
That's why I put in a reaction shot.
There's always a reaction shot in your films, isn't it?
That's why in scenes of 40-50 cuts, I make the attack and the defense reactions 50/50.
Young people say that's difficult. But as long as you remember to do it that way, I think it's the easiest.
"Blue Christmas" is also good.
There's always reaction shots in that one too.
I liked how there were never lines spoken off-camera.
Instead of a long take by a fixed camera,  it's keeps doing shot/reverse shot.
That's what's cool about "Blue Christmas."
No matter how small the reaction, it is shown.
For example even when Nakadai says "Oh" in reaction, it's shown.
That level of detail and thoroughness is great.
Invariably, if anything happens, a "yes" reaction is inserted.
I love cutting when "yes" is said.
I also when storyboarding, always end up inserting those cuts.
The staff say that's too much though.
But when I watched your work I had this feeling of closeness.
Thank you
That feeling was there, so...
If someone asked me who my favorite director was, I would say Kihachi Okamoto immediately.
It is a great honor.
But sometimes when I watch a film that has no reaction shots,
When the story goes on and on, I start to want to see the other party's reaction.
I wonder what kind of face they're making, and my head starts to hurt.
Recently, the style is to let the audience think about that.
Wondering if we've been giving them too much of that sense of closeness.
I've been thinking about how to intentionally not show the reactions.
Well you have no other choice if you're doing long takes.
Nevertheless, I'm getting a little tired of that, and I'm wondering if there's something new.
Eyeline
Lately, maybe I'm doing it on purpose, but I make an actor look the other way.
I know the direction of eyes should go this way, but I change the direction to that way.
In my opinion, the direction of eyes is very important.
For instance, I put in storyboards "eyeline this way."
I'm so influenced by you that I tend to make the character look into the camera.
Well, the direction of eyeline should be as near as possible.
Nevertheless, A still needs to look at B while speaking.
And B needs to look back at A in reaction.
In my work there's so many shots where the characters look into the camera,
that the artists are getting starting to hate me though.
Because it's hard to draw the face straight on. It's not easy.
It's also hard to act when the character looks into the camera.
But the eyelines that are close look more powerful, right?
Right. I like that they have energy.
The ones that shoot from the side,
the ones shot with a multi-cam setup...
There's a lot of these on TV, where one shot is done properly, and the other is done sloppily.
I'm not a big fan of cutting between profile shots and straight-on shots.
I prefer cutting between two straight-on shots, where both are looking at the camera.
Where I'm able to beautifully show the character's eyes' positions in the frame.
Drawings are at the end of the day two-dimensional, so the information is limited.
When a cut occurs, I feel that the viewers look for the character's eyes.
That's why I think acting by eyes is important, but unfortunately people don't pay enough attention to it.
It would be fine if they were doing it on purpose, but it doesn't look like that.
It's like they're not even aware of it.
Or they just don't care.
When I watch stuff like that it annoys me a bit.
Moreover, anime characters have big eyes.
Yes indeed.
There are practical reasons for that.
The character needs to be in symbolic form.
Otherwise, it ends up being a drawing that not all artists can draw.
But the good thing is that a character can act with eyes.
By changing the position of the pupil, etc.
Yes, but a drawing is just a drawing.
So when an animated character does serious acting,
it becomes cheap after a certain point. It loses believability.
The Director's Job
There are still some young directors who have aspirations.
Still now.
Yes, It's a few but I think we should count on them.
More than live-action, there's still some left in animation.
As for live-action, there was a recent live-action film called "Gamera",
Right. From Daiei Film.
I have a friend named Shinji Higuchi who does special effects,
Even though his staff don't get paid a lot, they're driven by the passion for the craft.
There are still some young people with ambition (willing to work hard for low pay) in live-action, but the medium's momentum is fading.
The number of films peaked in 1958, the year I became a director. I was shooting about three films in a year at that time.
If we shoot one movie every four years like we've been doing lately, I accumulate things I want to say, so the length of the film gets longer.
We think that films are entertainment,
but we still make films with the motive of "Let me say something here, even if it's just one thing."
For example, "Rainbow Kids".
The ¥10 billion scam itself is interesting too, but
At the end of the film, the kidnapped old lady mutters to herself, "What has my country done for me?"
That's it. I basically shot that whole film, all to say that one thing.
A director has two things. Something you want to say and something you want to do. I don't think I've done it completely,
But to a certain extent I've tried with the film "The Elegant Life of Mr. Everyman."
It's not a matter of whether it's good or bad, but it's my favorite.
But it's also the film the studio hated the most.
They got extremely angry, telling me, "We'll never let you write a script again."
All the films planned up until that point got shelved.
In reaction, I wrote "Nikudan."
There was no green light on the project, but I still wanted to write it.
The battle between the director and the studio is in many ways just as hard as the filmmaking, eh?
Yeah.
I think that's happening everywhere, unless you pay for it all yourself.
But it's still pretty relaxed here, compared to the US for instance.
That's because directors have the right of final cut here.
That right belongs to the producers in the US.
Eventually, they might order you to cut something.
Right, the person who's paying for everything...
That person is the strongest.
For us, as long as we pay some money, we don't fight over right of editing.
Editing is the only thing that is non-negotiable.
I once put negatives in my locker at home.
After I finish storyboarding, I can get someone to do the rough cut.
But as we discussed previously, with the issue of the 2-frames or 8-frames problem,
if I don't do the final cut myself, my rhythm won't show up in the film.
In the case of animation, sometimes I have to work on the storyline without drawings.
That's my duty, but it's tough indeed.
But editing is so interesting.
The trial and error at the end of the editing process is challenging and fun to do.
Again, depending on whether I cut out 2 frames or not, it changes everything.
Kihachi Okamoto & Hideaki Anno
END